okay if John is done that means we
should go ahead and start here uh 3
minutes that was not too long to wait I
think I'm pretty excited about Jon's new
language I hope you guys are too it's
the first time I've seen anyone who
really cares about the same sorts of
things that I care about uh try to make
a new language and so I'm pretty
optimistic I think uh maybe a year or
two from now I can do handmade hero in
jaai or something fun like that and I
think that would be a blast I'm sure
there's a bunch of cool stuff we could
do with it
anyway thank you uh for indulging me and
waiting the extra few minutes I wanted
to catch the uh the the whole thing joh
of John's uh
presentation but it is time now uh for
day 18 am I correct people I believe it
is day 18 of handmade hero the show
where we create an entire game
professional quality from scratch no
libraries no nothing so we can see how
every last little thing actually works
uh and to me that is very important
because I think it's crucial to really
kind of understand how everything works
even when you do uh then go on to use
libraries or use engines just having
that full uh perspective there that lets
you at any time drop down to a low level
and fix anything that you need to or to
understand why something might be going
wrong uh in code that you're using that
kind of stuff is just so valuable uh and
so we are going to do it all here on
this stream we're going to keep on uh
making sure we go into detail every last
little place we can so uh today on our
uh we've got a a pretty big to-do item
that we've got to do today and I don't
know if we're going to get it all in
today uh so but we're going to try and
basically what we have to do is we have
uh not actually done the work to make a
proper synchronized timing Loop to drive
our game so we could go ahead and make
our game uh on the platform layer that
we have now uh but we would be uh at
risk of having greater audio latency
than we should have we would be uh at
risk of sort of having just
synchronization problems there uh we
just haven't quite gotten to the point
where we really understand the timing of
when things show up on the screen and
when the audio plays out the speakers
and so I'd like to do a little
tightening there before we even start I
know I've said later that we're going to
go and have a pass on the win32 platform
layer when we're going to ship where we
do a bunch of things that we've been
putting off uh that are performance kind
of stuff that sort of thing and
compatibility stuff that we're not
addressing now but this I want to
address sooner rather than later because
all of the decisions that we make uh in
the actual game itself are all driven
off of this timing so when we are
playing the game when we are deciding
how long things should take in the game
uh every last thing we do uh is going to
be uh based on on um excuse me is going
to be based on whatever that clocking is
so if we have that clocking wrong in the
platform uh prototyping layer that we've
got now then we're at risk of making a
whole bunch of tuning things uh in
incorrect in our game and then when we
go to finalize the platform layer and
tighten all that stuff up then we have
this problem where oh now all the tuning
values that all of the stuff that we
tuned in our game and all of the stuff
that we thought was right for
playability of the game as we were
developing it is actually all wrong so
what we want to do is just take a little
bit of time now to go through and kind
of make it a little more coherent what
it's trying to do and make sure that we
understand that uh so that we can know
that we don't have any critical problems
that will lead us to make a bunch of bad
decisions that we have to kind of redo
later anyway uh yeah do someone on the
stream said don't forget to start
recording the problem there is I I did
forget to do the stop start recording so
that just means I it's it's really just
a convenience feature for me it just
means that I have to go through and take
the file and just clip out the first uh
little bit before I upload it to YouTube
so that the YouTube archive doesn't have
a bunch of me watching John on the
stream although who knows maybe it
should be a bunch of me watching John on
the stream but uh ignoring that so what
we need to do today is we need to go uh
take care of that so uh if you have
pre-ordered the game then you have
access to the source code you got an
email that has a link in it that link
allows you to download the source code
every night so I highly recommend you do
that because if you would like to follow
along with what we are doing today here
on day 18 you just unzip the day 17
piece out of your zip file that zip file
has every day is in there so you can
jump to any day you want uh and work on
it so if you're looking at this video uh
you want to be uh day 17 Source unzipped
that is what I am starting with and that
is what you should start with as well
all right so before we go and actually
do any coding what I want to do first is
take a look at the goals that we have
for uh what we're trying to what we're
trying to make I want to I want to
really kind of go over uh sort of the uh
the the high level picture so that
everyone understands what we're trying
to do now I took some recommendations
from folks uh and I downloaded uh this
package called Smooth draw uh which I
guess is is something that they use on
on Con Academy or something like this
just to see if it's any better than the
thing that uh that we were using the the
paint Microsoft Paint I I tried it a
little bit and honestly it doesn't seem
to actually be any better it seems to be
basically just the same thing uh as we
had before uh here it doesn't actually
seem to be all that much better but you
know what we'll give it a little shot
and we'll see how it plays out so what I
want to talk about is I want to go back
to that diagram sort of that I've been
using for quite sometime uh where I'm
talking about the various frames when
they're computed when they're displayed
that sort of thing so I'm going to make
some tick marks on our timeline here uh
like this and basically what we have
here is is this is T going forwards this
is time uh this is our timeline right
and the timeline you know I can I get a
can I get a can I get that little
smaller
timeline did that get smaller does feel
like it got much smaller I don't know
did you guys think that got smaller hard
to say let's go even smaller than that
timeline you know what this is just not
very good I don't know about this
program we'll give it a little more
we'll give it a little more time but I'm
not I'm not optimistic that this is
actually you know yeah what what what
can you
do something we can address a little
later perhaps anyway uh basically if we
take a look at what happens here uh we
start the game at some point uh that
we'll call t0 right and basically this
is when the game actually begins running
so the person runs the executable and we
got to do our Windows startup stuff and
all that sort of thing now at some point
we actually start the timing so we
actually take a look at what our timer
value actually is and that was query
performance counter was the thing that
we were using to measure time we're
going to take a look at what that timing
value actually is and when we take a
look at that that first timing sample we
take is going to be the first Benchmark
that we have for figuring out how much
wall clock time has elapsed during our
code so I'm going to call t0 that actual
time that is our first look at uh query
performance counter right that's our T
equals z now what's going to happen
there is during this first interval
during this interval here right uh
during that first interval we are going
to be displaying essentially nothing
right uh this is just plain Blackness on
the screen um we will if anything we
just have a cleared window there's
nothing there because we have not
actually prepared uh any actual uh any
anything really we haven't actually got
a frame buffer that we can show uh so
extending backwards as far as time uh
goes is some sort of Blackness and then
there's going to be some tick mark
That's the first tick mark where we
actually display a frame now if we want
to we can also call this t0 it depends
this this is again we're going to have a
bunch of decisions here we have a bunch
of decisions we could also call t0 uh
the first the um the first uh frame flp
right we could call it here right so I
don't know which one we want to call T
equals z we could call it this start we
could call it
here hard to say something we're going
to have to decide in a few minutes but
basically at some point during here uh
inside here we are Computing uh frame
zero right we are Computing frame zero
audio and video right we've got both of
those coming online so we're doing the
computation work inside this time
interval uh to compute those when they
are done we will then flip them so that
right here and coming forwards to here
in this interval you can actually see
frame zero displayed so on the screen
you will see frame zero right and
ideally what we'd also like to do is
have audio zero show up right along with
that right so we want audio zero uh to
come right here as well right I don't
know I don't know how you guys feel
about slashes through zero sometimes I
feel like it's a little classy you know
it feels a little European a little
fancy so so maybe I'll just go ahead and
put that in
there put that in
there
so what we've got now uh is we've
basically got a time interval uh this
could have been as long as we wanted
right because Blackness is on the screen
and no audio is playing so this is
silent Blackness right sounds like some
bad sci-fi movie Silent Blackness is
here and then once we start here we have
both audio and a frame on the screen so
what basically happens is this can be
arbitrarily long this this time interval
is arbitrarily long and we don't
actually care how long it takes it could
take an hour well I mean we care about
that because we don't want to keep the
user waiting obviously but it doesn't
matter how long it takes because there
isn't anything actually being displayed
so as far as the user knows they're not
going to see any glitches or hear any
glitches if this takes too long because
there's actually nothing going on it's
just starting up the the window has just
come come on screen but once we get to
here
this now we actually have some Target uh
for the amount of uh time that this is
going to be on the screen uh this is
basically a fixed duration here right
oops that's not very good this is
basically a fixed uh
duration that we have to compute the
next frame now I want to really
underscore why I say this is fixed
duration because there's a lot of uh
stuff like I don't know if you guys have
seen uh Nvidia has made some
announcements and there's been
announcements um on like other standards
and stuff about variable frame rate
displays
right excuse me basically normal
monitors excuse me like the kind you
would normally see uh from just today
normal monitors have some frame rate
that they update the image at and so
that frame rate whatever the monitor is
updating at
is also what we would like to update at
if the monitor is refreshing the image
right uh at 60 frames a second so that's
you know 16 milliseconds or so 16.6
something like 17 milliseconds a frame
right if you think about that uh we want
to synchronize with that presentation
because if we do something other than 60
SC milliseconds a frame then we will
essentially be offbeat with the monitor
so if you imagine the monitor has has
kind of a timeline down here as well if
it was updating at a different rate than
we were let's say a little bit less like
this right of course don't know if I can
WR got get that out of my head there we
go uh basically what will happen is
eventually we'll miss a frame so right
here it won't matter here it will dis it
will display this Frame here it will
display this Frame here it will display
this Frame but here it will display the
same frame again the monitor will and
we'll have to wait till a much longer
time than the user has used to been
seeing it's used to seeing this interval
now it's going to see this interval and
we're going to see we we we feel like we
skipped a frame to the user so we want
the monitor's uh refresh rate and our
refresh rate to be the same right we
want to update at roughly the same
frequency so we're consistent so that
every time the monitor goes to get a new
frame we give it a new frame that's the
goal so we can do that on either the
monitor's actual refresh rate like let's
say it's 90 Hertz or 120 HZ monitor we
can do that actually 120 HZ or we can do
it as some subdivision of that so let's
say we're updating our game at 60 um
frames a second and the monitor is 120
frames a second 120 Herz 60 HZ Hertz is
just cycles per
second well as long as we're a multiple
of two or something an even multiple
three whatever away from that then we
know that we're never going to hit that
beat frequency problem uh where we're
going to have problems of skipping a
frame as far as the monitor is concerned
and having user see a a apparent change
uh in animation
speed
sorry I uh made I made some homemade
almond milk today and I didn't do a very
good job it's kind of rough uh and it
kind of scratches your throat a little
bit I don't know how to fix that exactly
I got to think about it I'm still new at
making almond milk so yeah what are you
going to do it's not the storeo brand so
all right basically what I wanted to say
about that is that there's a lot of uh
talk now about variable refresh rate
monitors and basically what those are
monitors that can update at Whatever
frequency you want for the most part uh
so basically what happens is whenever
your frame is done you just say display
the frame right uh and so you might say
well why do we care about any of this
isn't isn't the future going to just be
you take as long as you need to to
display the frame and then you display
it isn't that fine and I don't
understand the attraction of that to me
that just sounds absolutely awful I do
not understand why anyone would ever
want such a monitor at all and the
reason that I say that is because I feel
like it always forces you to be
completely wrong with how you displayed
your animation and the reason I say that
is because imagine uh how the
computation cycle goes on one of these
variable frame rate monitors well I come
down here right and I'm basically saying
that I'm going to use a variable frame
rate so it looks uh something like this
you know who knows what it looks like
let's say it looks like that right so
we've got something here uh let's say uh
this is going to be you know uh
something like 30 milliseconds this is
going to be something like 16 this was
like 20 right and this was back to 30
again so we have a completely variable
uh a thing here so what happens uh we
know that 30 uh milliseconds has has
elapsed these are milliseconds here we
know that 30 millisecs has elapsed
between here and here right something
was on the screen here we don't know
what it was what we're saying this at
some point in time so it's with the
previous frame who knows what happened
so let's talk about starting here well
we know that the world uh updated 30
Mill seconds between here and here right
we know that 30 Mills of Time Has Gone
by so we need to tell the physics engine
uh for for whatever frame is that we're
going to display right here we would
want to tell it 30 milliseconds because
there is a state of the world here right
this is World state zero this is World
zero and now we need to display World
State one right we want to render what
the world looks like 30 milliseconds
into the future okay but there's a
problem we don't actually know this
value yet because we have a variable
frame rate monitor and we're going to
flip whenever we're done we have no idea
what the 30 milliseconds is and most of
this time is usually rendering like this
is rendering right here right so the
physics happens somewhere in here it's
got to know right away before we even
have any idea how long the frame rate is
it's got to know how much to update the
World by how does it know to pick 30
milliseconds well it doesn't so it
probably looks at the previous frame for
a guess well if it looks at the previous
frame it's always going to be wrong it's
going to look at 30 milliseconds here
but surprise this took 16 milliseconds
so now you've got a world that appears
to be moving twice as fast then we go
here we look and it's oh it's it
actually turns out to be 20 but we
thought it was going to be 16 so this is
actually a world that appears to be
moving slightly slower blah blah blah
right so I do not understand I don't I
do not get it people who believe in this
technology uh please feel free to write
in and tell me what the attraction is
because I do not see it at all as far as
I'm concerned you need to know what you
expect your frame rate to be in the
future and you need to guarantee that
you're going to hit that frame rate in
order to get a smooth uh believable
looking non- hipy sort of Animation uh
unless you just don't care you know and
so this I think is very important so
what I would say is variable update uh
monitors might be useful if your frame
rate if you can guarantee your frame
rate but you happen to know it's always
45 milliseconds let's say of course that
would be pretty bad so let's say it's
something like 20 you know it's always
20 milliseconds well that's fine then as
long as you're fixing that rate but
really a variable refresh rate monitor
doesn't actually help you in during the
course of your game what you all all you
really can use is something that's
essentially a fixed rate monitor where
you can set the rate um and so that that
I think is kind of mostly all I I wanted
to convey about that is I don't really
understand uh the attraction uh of those
things much at all and I think if any
they're only good because they allow
games to run at other frame other fixed
frame rates that aren't uh 30 60 90
basically uh maybe you can get you know
you can use 70 or something uh and you
maybe you couldn't do that before uh in
any realistic way uh so I don't
know just something to think about want
to get that out there uh so maybe I'm uh
maybe I'm thinking about it the wrong
way but i' that's always been my problem
with that whole concept so um for me
whenever I do a game Loop uh and I'm
looking at timing stuff I always want to
have a Target frame rate and we try very
hard to hit that frame rate and if for
some reason we're not hitting that frame
rate we pick a new lower frame rate and
we're always trying to stay fixed at
whatever that frame rate is so if we're
trying to run at 60 and we can't run at
60 we drop down to 30 or something like
that and again maybe that's where you
know these variable frame mins could
come in they allow us to change our
fixed frame rate but I never want the
frame rate to be variable I never ever
ever want that because there's no way to
actually make that work properly your
physics is always wrong if you do that
uh so what I want to do is I want to
make a frame Loop uh that basically
obeys uh this sort of um thing where
it's going to Fe it's going to have an
opinion about the frame rate it can hit
right so it knows how many milliseconds
that is we'll call that uh the target
milliseconds so we know what our Target
milliseconds is right the target
millisec comes in the physics updates
the world right so we get our update
here uh it's it's the target Mill drives
our update we do our render and then we
do our page flip of that render right as
a close to the boundary of the target
Mill seconds as we can right then we do
the same thing over again for the next
uh thing and now this may be pipelined
so remember uh this may go off to a GPU
or something which actually delays
everything by a frame while it chews
through it or whatever that's fine as
long as we are always pushing it at a
synchronous thing uh and we set it to
synchronize say with a with the uh with
the vertical blank or whatever that the
monitor
refresh we'll still be just fine as long
as we always know that we're updating
with a particular Target in mind and
that Target matches our flip rate and
that is what we're trying to do now for
the audio uh we have a slight uh other
problem here the problem with the audio
is ideally what we'd like to do is feed
just exactly the amount of audio that we
need every frame uh but if we do that we
do run the risk of if we Miss like let's
say we missed uh for our our 30
millisecond time right so we actually
missed and we're going to have a frame
lag well our audio would skip here so we
have two choices uh because you know we
basically need to make sure the audio is
always there on time we have two choices
always get the audio there on time
meaning our frame rate is a hard
constraint and we've basically written
the game to never miss frame
rate the other one is always feed the
audio somewhat further ahead and there's
two methods of doing this one method is
just to like to be a frame of lag off
right or something or or half a frame of
lag off right uh in order to handle a
whole frame miss you kind of got to be
uh a whole frame of audio ahead right so
that would encour 60 milliseconds or 30
milliseconds depending on the frame rate
uh this is at 60 HZ and this is at 30 HZ
I should probably start saying 17
because it's really it's 16.6 repeating
right uh it's it's 1,00 divid 16
but you know what I mean when I say 16
it's code word for
17 16 and a half whatever uh you know
what I'm saying anyway uh basically what
happens
here is uh I'm introducing audio latency
so I could try to reduce that audio
latency by doing one of two things one
thing I can do is always feed two frames
of audio but when I do hit my target
when I do find that I wake up and I've
got plenty of time to update the audio
so I'm here and I go okay I've got
plenty of time to the audio update it as
uh overwrite the old stuff that I wrote
right so basically uh always always give
it an extra frame but don't uh use that
extra frame if we have time we'll just
Splat a new one right that's one way of
doing it uh another way of doing it um
is uh like I said to to just always
actually write one whole frame ahead uh
and a final way of doing it would be to
have like a thread or something that's
sitting there waiting and it looks to
see if we've updated by like right here
and if we haven't it emergency flushes
another frame of audio right so it's
kind of like a guard right so we've got
we got a couple options we've basically
got one always hit you know we've got
always hit the frame rate we've got um
uh
overwrite the frame uh overwrite the
next
frame we've got a frame of
lag and we've got a guard thread
and there may be even other methods
those are just the ones that I happen to
know about and have ever seen used or
used
myself so I'm not 100% certain that I
can honestly argue directly for any one
of these in particular it's kind of hard
to say I think the one that I would
rather go with because it's simpler and
it enforces sort of a little bit of
discipline would just be going with
option one option one is the easiest
option is to always hit your frame rate
right and one of the things that's
interesting about that that I like is I
like the mentality of saying that this
game has to hit its frame rate instead
of just allowing it like oh it kind of
gets slow sometimes and we don't want to
optimize the when the explosion happens
or whatever and it get slow so we'll
just let it get slow there and we'll
we'll compensate by having the frame
rate looks crappy but the audio doesn't
skip so we're happy right I don't love
that I feel like if we write a game uh
and the user is being reasonable so they
playing our game and not running like
another game in the background or
something where they deserve to hear
some audio skips if that's where they're
going uh I would prefer kind of to say
we always hit our frame rate so you know
we target 30 HZ let's say um and we
always get there and if we don't hit 30
HZ then that means we have to optimize
whatever it is that's making us not hit
30 HZ uh so I'm tempted to go with this
one first I think that might be which
one I go with first but I wanted to
mention these other ones because maybe
we'll have to switch to them if we find
that we're unsatisfied with what I'm
talking about here
uh or uh you may choose when you're
implementing this uh basically to
uh to uh go with a different option
because you care about different things
because many things in programming
there's not a right answer there's
simply a question of your priorities uh
and those priorities will lead you to to
make a certain decision or a different
decision and you can't really say that
the decision was wrong or right you can
only say if it was wrong or right based
uh with respect to some priority system
so there you go hopefully that makes
some
sense so we need to do a couple things
that we're not doing right now in order
to make this happen the first thing that
we're going to have to do is we have to
figure out some way of knowing um or at
least getting some idea of what the
monitor refresh rate even is because we
want to run at that refresh rate uh and
so we kind of have to go ahead and take
a look at um at ways to figure out what
the refresh rate is of the monitor that
we're actually using now to be honest I
haven't done this in a long time and I
did write down some notes about how I
used to do it um but it's going to be a
little dicey and the reason for that is
I don't really know uh all the stuff
that happens essentially with sort
of with multiple monitor scenarios so if
you take a look uh basically here here's
the um here's the thing that I was
thinking about uh can actually see get
monitor refresh rate let's just take a
look here where is our msdn msdn here it
is let's take a look here uh I'm pretty
sure that some of these are just not uh
actually well okay this this might work
so this might actually work because it
does take the HDC so we'd be able to
pass our Windows device context handle
uh and let's see if this is going to be
something that we think uh is a reliable
value I don't actually know if it is or
not but we can sort of see so here we go
the current vertical refresh rate of the
device in cycles per second uh so
basically this um yeah a vertical
refresh rate value of zero or one
represents the display Hardware's
default refresh rate uh so that's not
really useful right that's not going to
tell us we actually need it to say
something like uh 60 or something like
that that's if it's if it's just going
to tell us um if it's just going to tell
us something nonsens like that that's
not going to help us so we can enumerate
we can also enumerate the monitors try
to find it from there I'm not entirely
sure um I'm not entirely sure what the
best way to do it is nowadays this is
this is a good question um and I'm not
super prepared to to answer it
so yeah yeah I don't know um I don't
usually trust the stack uh overflow
answers I found them to be wrong a lot
of time uh so I don't tend to look at
these very often um and this doesn't
look particularly convincing here either
so I don't know I'm going to go ahead
and say uh that I'm just going to do uh
I'm just going to go with en numing the
monitors this is the kind of thing that
I do nowadays and I haven't really
played around with refresh rates too
much but I just want to kind of um I
feel like this might be the most useful
way uh to go because I think this will
probably give us a way to get it so I'm
going to take a look at this basically
enom display monitors is the thing that
allows us to see um basically all of the
things uh in the system that are
monitors that that can be displaying
graphics and I believe we can do a
pretty uh easy way to uh to actually get
the one that we're on as well well so uh
let me take a look at this then when we
call get monitor we can call get monitor
info on those and I believe that sort of
thing will be able to to allow us to ask
for uh stuff about the refresh rate I'm
not actually sure uh that that's
actually true uh but I think it might be
so let's take a look here monitor
info yeah we can let's see still not
still not the case let's see get refresh
rate of H monitor because I'd really
like to be able to do it uh from here if
possible because I just don't I just
don't actually trust uh the other thing
yeah so you
[Music]
can yeah I don't know I'm sorry I'm
Heming and Hauling so much here I just a
lot of times these things are pretty
crazy so basically
um excuse me looks like the this uh
device mode uh structure here would
actually tell us what it is we want to
know so let's just see if we can get one
of those uh relatively easily um from
from the Monitor and whether that gives
us back I'll just test it whether it
gives us back uh the actual information
that we want it looks like it probably
would uh so let's take a look here
um height display frequency right so is
that defined let's see what msdn says
again msdn can definitely be wrong but
it's usually my first go-to I trust it
more than sack overflow anyway um so
let's take a look here
frequency what that basically says is
this value is also known blah blah blah
when you call this the May return with
value Z ah what is with this zero and
one thing well all right I guess I'm not
sure what way I can really definitively
say what the monitor refresh time
actually is it does not seem to be
something that's forthcoming um so I
don't know that's that's kind of that's
kind of disappointing to me um normally
so I mean just to be clear the reason
that this doesn't normally come up is
normally what happens in open jilo
direct 3D is you set them into a mode
where they flip on the monitor refresh
anyway so when you do that all you have
to do to figure out what your refresh
rate is is time how long it takes to
flip in one of those two things and then
you roughly know what the graphics card
is doing uh that's pretty
straightforward and not that difficult
but in this case if we actually want to
know because we're doing the flip we're
doing the blit ourselves uh so we don't
really have that that freedom the way
you would use to do it is with direct
draw um but direct draw is kind kind of
old and deprecated I don't know we could
try to do it uh direct draw get vertical
refresh this is the way that I used to
do it in the old days we could we could
try to do it I don't actually know um
whether that will be sort of um whether
that will actually be accurate though
when we ask for a particular monitor uh
vertical refresh so let's see um what it
actually says here I don't know what
this is this is some crazy stuff here um
let's see anything particularly
interesting here uh no this this looks
totally that looks totally off the rails
um this is the msdn page but it's for
the flip call so I don't actually know
if that's something particularly useful
and it's it's Windows mobile so that's
not going to do it yeah I don't know
this may be have something we'll have to
save uh for tomorrow and we'll just have
to put in the value I'll go look at my
old code that uses direct draw and we
can try it uh unless there's some better
way to do it uh that we can find because
we can't really if if we can't rely on
of these things to to not give us back
01 I'm not sure uh what we can really do
uh because if you look at like I don't
know if we look at this code it doesn't
look particularly uh it doesn't look
particularly useful there's really
nothing you can do there um the default
refresh rate is not something that that
seems to be defined anywhere uh so
anyway excuse me uh we'll we'll have to
tackle that tomorrow I guess and I'll
just I guess I'll do the direct I'll
guess I'll do the direct 3D version I
mean I'm sorry the direct draw version I
don't know what else oh that's not the
command prompt we want we have our own
custom command prompt there we go well
that's disappointing I was hoping that
there would be an easy way to get it but
it looks like there isn't that's the
that's the sad State uh sometimes of
operating systems something like getting
the monitor refresh rate should be just
like one call you're like here's the the
monitor I'm on tell me what the refresh
rate is and it should guaranteed to give
you back the refresh rate uh and I do
not know how we get into situations
where that is not um the the sort of the
standard thing to happen but you know
what are you going to do that's just
that's just life as a programmer in the
platform layer it's one of the reasons
we'll be very happy to get off the
platform layer next week so we don't
have to deal with stuff like this all
right so basically what we're going to
have to do is we're going to have to
assume that we make up a refresh rate
and so for now we'll just call we'll say
that there's a refresh rate up here uh
we'll say that this is a refresh or
monitor refresh Hertz uh and that will
be just 60 for now right so we'll just
say it's 60 refreshes per second
and we'll say to do um how do we
reliably query
this on Windows because we don't know um
maybe direct draw is still the way to do
it which would be kind of scary because
direct draw is deprecated uh so that
would that would not be my preference
but what are you going to do all right
so then what we can do is from that we
can compute some synthetic values right
we know uh that from that we can compute
how much much time we expect to go by uh
in seconds for every frame uh so
basically the uh seconds elapsed per
frame right is going to be uh the
milliseconds 1,000 milliseconds per
frame divided by that monitor refresher
Hertz right that's going to give us how
many seconds are elapsed every frame so
uh I guess the other thing we should say
is uh we need we we have a game uh
update Hertz as well right and I sort of
was saying that we probably don't want
it to be the monitor refresh rate
because we're going to not probably hit
60 uh when we're doing software
rendering so maybe let's say that this
is 30 as well uh and basically we'll
derive this from this once we actually
get to someplace where we can get this
value so you know for now we'll say it's
it's it's that divided by two or
something like that so really uh the
second elapse per frame is actually
going to be our games update Hertz
because we'll probably be only uh
flipping every other time so that's how
much we want to actually have elapsed so
the first thing we need to do is
actually measure this uh which we
already kind of put in the basis of and
then we want to actually wait uh until
we get to the point uh where we're at
this uh this time elapsed and then we
can go
ahead and sort of um delay if you will
our page flip to just the right time so
that we get you know 60 frames second uh
or in this case 30 frames second
whatever our game updates hurts is so
what we want to do is down here
somewhere right after we've done
everything remember we we have a thing
we already kind of put a thing in here
where we uh query performance
counter so we know how much time has
elapsed uh and we were printing that out
before we were printing that out right
here so we basically have a uh a value
which is the counter elapsed and we
actually did the milliseconds per frame
thing here uh and so what we want to do
here is change up what we're doing a
little bit uh what we want to do here is
say how how much time uh has actually
elapsed um so far right so uh seconds
elapsed for um compute basically for for
for work let's say how much we actually
had to do uh and we know what that value
is that's this right here uh so we're
going to go ahead and do that and that's
just this um particular thing we don't
actually care about this uh the 32 bit
I'm sorry the 64 bit of that because
we've already done the subtract so
that's all good so once we do that uh we
basically have um and we don't need the
Thousand anymore because that's that was
to compute millisec so really all we
need to do is divide the time that
elapsed uh by the frequency of that of
our count of our clock of that Windows
reported for our clock and that will
give us back how many seconds elapsed uh
during the work that we did for our
frame right now what's going to happen
here is that's going to be different uh
than the other value the the value that
we basically uh computed up here which
is how much seconds we want to elapse
per frame so this is the seconds lapse
per frame Target and we could actually
call that Target seconds laps per frame
or Target seconds per frame something
like that right uh so we have a Target
seconds per frame and we're going going
to see uh like basically how much time
we have left so assuming uh we're always
trying to be under it
right so we're
assuming that we essentially have uh we
we almost want to have sort of a while
loop here right we want to kind of say
while uh the seconds
elapsed we could even think uh yeah in
fact I'm going to change this back to so
far because we could just go ahead and
uh no you know what cuz we're going to
want to print that out never mind I'm
going to save it that way that was good
uh so I'm going to do seconds elapsed uh
for frame right and we'll start that off
uh by saying we're going to actually be
doing this this query performance
counter we're going to be doing this
actually inside the loop so we're going
to take a look at the second cpse for
work we're going to say that we're going
to start with that and we're go in here
and say if the second topse per frame is
less than what we actually wanted so if
it's less than the Target right then
we're going to take some action um to
basically make sure that we are uh not
going too fast so we're basically going
to going to slow things down so the
first thing we can do and this is just
the CPU melting version is we can just
do this again right we can just go ahead
and and and fullon do this sort of thing
now you can see that this is going to
start to get messy if I keep doing
something like this where I keep uh you
know I keep checking and checking and
checking so we're going to probably want
to pull this out into utility function
but for now uh we should probably be
fine so what we'll do is we'll just keep
getting uh the end counter over and over
we'll look at the counter elapsed and
then we'll basically do the seconds
lapse for frame computation we'll just
do it inside this Loop right we'll just
keep on doing it and doing it and doing
it and so what we should do uh oops
don't want to Define that again uh what
we basically should do here um and you
know what I can even do I don't even
need to do that I can just stick that
right in there there we go and make that
divide a little clearer there we go uh
so basically what we can do is just keep
on doing this and until we get to uh the
time when we actually get a above the
target seconds per frame right and then
we can go ahead and do our flip So in
theory if we actually do that now uh in
fact we should actually that that should
actually just be basically a a locked
Loop uh that forces us to update at 60
frames a second uh now we can we'll have
to verify that that's actually true um
but let's just go ahead and make that
happen
here where we there we go let's see why
am I not
um why am I not getting any input here
that does not look reassuring I feel
like we should be getting some input but
we are getting no input whatsoever that
doesn't sound good something has gone
horribly horribly wrong I suspect that
probably this while loop was busted hold
on one second while seconds elapse for
frame gives less than Target seconds per
frame uh no that should be what did I do
wrong it's off to a good start in the
Stream today when the first thing I type
in is already lousy but you know
programming is like that some days some
days you're on and some days you're off
and on days when you're off it just
means you got to do a lot more debugging
and you know when it happens um but you
know what can you do you just got to you
just got to you got to chin up you know
and and and and get through it anyway uh
let's let's go in here and step in the
debugger hopefully it'll be relatively
obvious uh what I messed up there
because we're not actually uh updating
so I think what's happening is this this
while loop uh is uh is never actually
making this get big enough for what it
should be so oh well that was easy looks
like we left a uh yeah that's good
that's stupid all right uh what I
basically did there is I computed the
target milliseconds per frame instead of
the target seconds per frame so that's
that's pretty much the entirety of the
bug uh not not particularly interesting
to say the least so uh okay in theory uh
we should actually be going at somewhat
more of a consistent frame rate but I
don't actually know if that's true we
should be going at 30 now but I'm not
sure if that's true that that audio is
skipping like crazy so I'll have to take
a look at what's going on there uh so
let's take a look here at that while
loop make sure that's actually running
properly uh oh so this is wrong as well
so this end counter has to actually be
done uh outside so let's let's go ahead
and pull I don't know if you could see
what was happening there but basically
we need we need to update our last
counter to be proper I mean the fix is
is very simple it's it's this right here
uh but let's this code is now super
messy so I'm going to go ahead and pull
that out uh let's see if that makes a
little bit
better
okay yeah so that looks that looks more
correct all right but uh this is still
super ugly here so we got to pull this
out so let's start um by by pulling out
this uh the clocking stuff into
something that's a little more
understandable right uh so let's
basically say first of all I kind of
want to go ahead and say um that the uh
the query performance frequency this
thing right here uh I kind of want the
query performance frequency to basically
be something that can be always accessed
since we comput it once I want that to
be just like a global variable uh that's
just whatever the frequency is and we
initialize it at startup so what I would
like to do at least is have uh this this
variable basically right I'd like this
to be um a global so I'd like that to be
a a global variable so the perf count
frequency uh is basically going to be uh
this thing here let's see that we had it
at before per count frequency um so
basically we just want a global variable
that always lets us know what that
frequency is so that we clear it once
and then we can use it outside in a
different uh in a different context and
so then what we have uh is we basically
have our excuse me we have our actual
call uh that does our computation we
want that to be uh something that's kind
of nicely encapsulated so I'm just going
to pull it out here and I'm basically
going to uh have a way of saying snap us
a counter in various places and then
take a difference of them uh so
basically uh I want something here which
is basically you know it's just an
inline function that's going to do a get
seconds elapsed something like this uh
and it will take two different uh um
ones of these so uh start and end let's
say like that so it'll take the start
and end and it'll do uh this computation
properly it'll know that basically
whatever the elapsed time is here um you
know it'll do end uh quad part minus
start. quad part it'll do this this uh
reliably so we know we don't have a typo
or anything in it we can debug it once
and make sure it's right um basically
we'll just do that seconds elapsed it'll
do that computation and then return it
uh so there we go like
that so that's fine and then we also uh
will have one which are B which is
basically just a way to uh to get a
clock value so win 32 get uh get wall
clock basically that will actually do uh
this query performance counter and just
return that value uh directly uh so that
way at least we can see it's it's a
little clearer what we're actually
trying to do with it uh and we can go
ahead and return that there we go so now
we can replace our stuff with this uh
and hopefully it will all be good so
perf count frequencies there uh let's go
ahead and put this up with our globals
and we'll call that Global perf count
frequency so perf count frequency uh and
that should never never changed during
the Run of our program so we should be
good to go now uh in here we need to
replace our uh all of our stuff that we
were doing for query performance counter
what we actually want to do here is say
Okay
um our last uh counter is equal to win
32 get wall clock right like that uh and
we can leave our rdts for now we're
going to do something else with those
later but rdtsc is is very processor
specific so you can't really use that uh
for timing uh if you're you can't use
that for timing that runs on the user's
machine you can only use Query
performance counter for actually timing
stuff on the on the user machine so our
game code has to be driven off of query
performance counter rdtsc is only for
timing code for
profiling because how it behaves varies
from CPU to CPU and all sorts of other
stuff so you don't want to ship a game
that uses rdtsc for actual um game time
all right uh so then we get down here we
can say uh this is basically our work
counter so our work counter uh wi 32 get
wall clock we'll get that there uh then
we have uh what was our that was our
cycles that can go up there till we deal
with it later uh so we have our work
counter there uh and we want to know our
seconds elapsed our uh let's just call
this work seconds elapsed like that we
can say win 32 get second elapsed and
we'll give that uh between our work
counter basically work counter uh and
our last
counter so that's the the actual last
counter that gets updated uh at the very
end
so think that's roughly right what I
want to do then I'm going to go through
here and this is going to be our work
seconds elapsed right we're going to go
through here and say we're going to
update our um check counter basically
and that's going to get the wall clock
time here get wall clock like that uh
and then we're going to get the seconds
elapse wi 32 get seconds elapsed and
we're going to try to time in between
the last counter uh and our check
counter right and we can also just
basically do this right uh which is kind
of nice having functions encapsulate our
stuff is nice because it just makes the
code so much read more readable right so
we can basically just sit
here and keep going uh in fact we could
even be even more ridiculous if we
really wanted to and put that expression
right here uh but I don't think we need
to go that far that doesn't seem useful
so we let's not do that quite yet anyway
I'm going to if zero out all these
things for now because we're not dealing
with them at the moment then at the end
here at the very end uh we need to
update our last counter uh so basically
what we can do is we can say uh that our
end counter here large integer end
counter equals when 3 to get wall clock
which is what we wanted uh and then we
can set the last counter equal to that
now the this this guy here uh I'm going
to leave all these guys together and
stick them down at the very end um this
stuff needs to probably be cleaned up a
little bit but yeah let's let's move all
that down there okay so that should be
about right uh I think that looks about
right now of course the problem is at
the moment we don't really have a good
way uh to tell even whether like what
we're even running at like we have no
actual way of knowing uh what our actual
frame rate even is and so that's a
little bit of a problem uh to say the
least uh when you actually look at it um
you know it does it look consistent now
um you know sure right but how do you
really know and so what we kind of want
to do is probably have some way of
actually trying to verify that and one
thing we could do and I think this is
probably what we should do in maybe in
the remaining time is put a little
counter that just goes up every frame
that we can actually time with you know
like a stopwatch or something and verify
that in like a minute's worth of time
that it is actually gone up by the
amount that we should think that it
should right by you know 60 times our
frame rate so 60 time 30 or whatever it
is uh but maybe I don't know maybe we'll
do that tomorrow we're getting kind of
low on time here so let's just keep
going with what I was talking about here
so what we do want to do is we kind of
want to say here even though this is
while loop work will work just fine uh
there's a couple other things we want to
do here first of all excuse me what we
do want to do is we want to actually
verify that we didn't miss a frame so in
the if seconds the lasts what we' like
to do is put an else at the end of this
while right but you can't actually do
that in C so what we want to do here is
say okay if the seconds elapsed per per
frame was actually higher um than the
target then we've got a problem right
because if it's actually a little bit
higher that means we missed our frame
rate uh and so this is something we want
to do here uh that says missed frame
rate you know uh that's that and we
could we could even do uh an assertion
here uh but the problem is the insertion
would lock up so what we'd really like
to do is is this this will be um uh a
thing that will log and we'll be able to
see that actually pretty soon uh I don't
know if we'll do logging next week but
pretty
soon we'll be able to start seeing some
of these things that we wanted to log
but we don't have a system for yet so
the other thing we want to do is this
will basically just melt the CPU if that
makes sense um basically even if the CPU
did all the work that it needed to do
for the entire frame in a millisecond um
it's still going to sit here in this
spin lock doing a ton of work constantly
checking uh the performance counter
right it's it's just like wasting CPU
time so what we'd rather do is we'd
rather see if there's a any time left
that we can actually use to just sleep
uh just tell the operating system to put
the CPU to rest or do other work that it
has to do uh so what we'd like to do is
use this command um from msdn sleep
which basically excuse me which
basically just takes a number of
milliseconds and it waits it basically
just waits for that number of millisec
so what we would like to do here uh is
basically say let's do that sleep um for
the milliseconds you know sleep
milliseconds basically right and so in
here we're going to say uh that we have
a sleep milliseconds and the Sleep
milliseconds is going to be how many
milliseconds we could afford to sleep
right we're going to say all right we'll
take the target seconds per frame okay
like that we'll take the seconds elapsed
per frame we'll subtract them right uh
why did that not copy there we go
seconds lapse per frame uh we'll
multiply that by a th000
right because this is in seconds and now
we've got milliseconds and that's how
many milliseconds are left right that's
how many milliseconds are left to wait
um what we want to do now is that's
going to be a fractional value obviously
excuse me and so we only want to uh we
basically want to truncate that if that
makes sense um we want to sort of um oh
you know what I forgot too I forgot this
right here uh there we go we we we need
to actually wait uh to display the frame
this would actually have displayed the
frame and then waited which is not
particularly useful uh so what we want
to do here yeah is we want to go ahead
and see how many milliseconds we can
sleep uh so to do that we're going to go
ahead and truncate this fractional value
we're going to truncate the fractional
value out to a dword uh after we compute
it and so that will give us how much we
can sleep and then we will sleep now
there is a huge problem though uh with
doing this unfortunately uh which we
probably won't see when we run it here
but it's there you'll just have to take
my word for it oh well you can kind of
yeah you can no you can't really see it
and it's it's it's something that it's
hard to see um when we don't actually
have something running and when you're
not in certain circumstances and
whatever um there's because there's a
whole bunch of stuff that ties into this
but we'll get to those in a
second the problem is that basically
this sleep function in
Windows has a certain
granularity uh with how long it can can
actually put your thread to sleep so if
it decides when you call it that it's
going to put your thread to sleep
meaning your thread will no longer be
executing it is going to wait uh for the
next schedular
granularity to wake you up now what that
means uh for those of you unfamiliar
with operating systems is inside at
every operating system there's some code
called a scheduler and auler is what
decides when threads run like when
different processes run when the threads
run it's basically the thing that makes
your system preemptively multitask it's
the thing that lets you run a bunch of
different uh programs at once and it dos
out the work um it dos out the CPU time
to each of these programs to allow them
to do the work right but what happens is
that scheduler uh basically has to be
sort of a thing that interrupts what's
going on if you imagine you have one
program running and you need to let the
CPU do some work on another program then
the operating system you imagine has to
like interrupt right it has to jump in
and say okay stop the process hold on
that you're doing like emac let's say
stop emac hold it I got to go run the
code for this timer overlay that Casey
wrote right or something like this if
that makes
sense so if you think about what happens
there however frequently that scheduler
wakes up um is the maximum is the
minimum amount of time you could sleep
for because if your thread goes to sleep
it's not going to wake back up again
until the scheduler comes back on the
CPU and looks to see uh and goes oh he
wanted to wake up in X milliseconds X
milliseconds have elapsed so I'll wake
him up but if the scheduler only wakes
up let's say every 15 milliseconds and
you ask to sleep for 2 milliseconds well
you're actually going to sleep for 15
milliseconds because the scheduler ain't
going to wake up every two milliseconds
and
look excuse me so we can fix this it's
not a perfect fix but we can fix this we
can fix it with something called time
begin period
now what time begin period is it's a
weird I don't I don't even want to know
how this ended up being the way to do
this you can sort of see how but oh my
Lord You' think there'd be something
called set schuer granularity but no um
what actually happens is time begin
period is like a old multimedia system
call uh for about for setting when you
would get call back timers and what
resolution they had to be and of course
the call back timers couldn't happen at
a timer granularity unless the scheduler
was waking up at that granularity so it
ends up setting the schedule granularity
in Windows and it sets it uh to whatever
this period is here
right so that period is in milliseconds
which means the schedule granularity we
can set all the way down to 1
millisecond which is fine because we're
only going to sleep at a millisecond
granularity anyway uh I don't know if
that makes sense uh but hopefully it
makes sense I don't actually remember to
be honest with you it's been a long time
I don't actually remember uh how you
make this call it it it escapes me at
the moment but we'll go ahead and put it
in here excuse me so basically you call
time begin period and uh you pass it the
millisecond granularity that you want
excuse me so basically desired scheduler
uh
millisecond that is one just so we can
just so people reading this code knows
what's going on Note Casey set
the
windows
granularity to 1
millisecond uh so that our
sleep can be more
granular so let's do that uh so there we
go and now I just can't the only thing I
can't remember is whether you need uh to
actually well you know what you know
what I
think yeah you know what I think I think
there is one of the thing that we want
to do I'm just it's it's the old the
memory is kind of you know it jogs uh I
don't actually remember uh let's see uh
if there is I thought like there was a
way we could figure out to verify that
was right well we can look at the H
result at the very least so if this mm
result thing that comes back uh if that
returns time no error successful uh I
like Tim or no can do that's interesting
someone had a sense of humor there so
basically if that uh does this then it's
okay to sleep um or I should say sleep
is is granular is true um in fact we
could just do this we could just record
this um like that rle 32 sleep is
granular equals that so there you can
sort of see I'm just basically recording
whether this worked so if if it believed
it could set it uh then we'll then we'll
set it now the thing that the reason
that I wanted to record what it is is
because I don't want to introduce this
sleep if the operating system isn't
going to be able to do it so basically I
want to do if sleep is granular then
allow the sleep otherwise don't allow
the sleep does that make sense uh now
that was a like I said a multimedia
function so in order to link with that
uh we have to link with the multimedia
Library uh which is pretty Tri to do and
is this on all windows so that's not a
risk it's not a linking risk uh I
believe it's win mm. lib just yeah it is
of course remember uh you can always
determine that by going down here but
sometimes I like to see if I still
remember so all right now we have
basically gotten that working um our
sleep should be more granular um but we
still have no idea whether this is
working right or not like we've got no
idea uh and so so we can't really make
any conclusions yet but we're out of
time for the day
um so this may be incredibly buggy uh we
don't know but at least we've gone
through the theory of what we're trying
to do we've started uh to make ourselves
try to Target lock to a frame rate uh so
that's good and uh tomorrow we should be
able to go through and actually clean up
the audio side of things and do some
testing to verify that we're actually
running at the frame rate we think we
are uh because all of this stuff um is
probably uh buggy before we test it so
not tested yet probably
buggy right uh so we will do that you
know we could do as well um we could go
in here as a very simple test not a
particularly great one but we can go in
here as well and turn this back on uh
this would give us a little bit of of a
a sort of an idea if you will of of
what's actually going on um it would do
our old print out that we had uh so
counter elapsed uh we would just need to
go um like this here uh counter elapsed
milliseconds per frame like that so the
millisecond for frame is Win 32 uh get
wall clock or sorry get seconds elapsed
like that
1,000 that and then we would just do end
counter
last counter like that uh so that would
give us at least a little bit of an idea
uh what's going on uh in we don't
actually need or do we that's Global
that's that counter elapsed uh we don't
actually have that unfort okay so let's
get rid of the frame rate here uh for
now Al that's easy for us to compute
again uh so let's just go ahead and zero
that out we'll do that in a second and
buffer is redefinition we've already got
a buffer not surprising uh let's see
where that was buffer well actually yes
I don't care we'll just do FPS buffer
and then we're done so I'm just turning
this on as the last little thing we do
in the Fram just so we can take a look
um oh good it's telling us a warning
about this well what do you want me to
use I guess it's basically giving us a
security warning here and that security
warning is because you might have a
buffer overrun which is fine but this is
debug code I wish it wouldn't do that we
could turn off that warning uh but I
believe uh there should be some kind of
a of a guarded printf uh you would think
oh it still thinks that's unsafe what
would you like me to use underscore S I
guess so you want me to use this what do
you want me to use all right well
hopefully that works basically they they
they try to increase security by doing
these things and they often fail and
they end up just annoying you but you
know they were trying at least they were
trying to do some security security uh
so we look like we're pretty close we've
got a ways to go uh before we're
actually really accurate but it looks
like we're sort of getting our our 33.33
3333333 uh we have some reasons why we
won't um basically the thing that we
haven't done yet uh is we don't include
this this time information properly and
some other various things that we're not
doing properly uh so there's definitely
some other stuff that we want to kind of
do to try and make that a little more
accurate but at the moment uh it looks
like we're pretty good so we're we're
we're getting there so that's good with
that uh we are now at the where we
should be at the Q&A because we started
3 minutes late and it's 9:03 now uh so
we should be right where the Q&A should
be so let's go
ahead and uh do some Q&A here I'm going
to open up the twitch chat please make
sure to put uh C murator in your
question somewhere so I can see it and
please keep the questions to stuff we've
done on this stream or in some previous
stream because stuff about future
uh is stuff we'll get to in the future
uh so all right let's go ahead and see
what we have for
questions let's
see if we are locking the frame rate
won't that mean that this engine will
slow down the entire game if a person
has a bad computer and cannot hit our
frame rate uh yeah so we're not locking
the frame rate that's kind of a
that's not really what we're trying to
do here what we're trying to do is run
at a fixed frame rate so what we will do
as we go forward is in this code this
right here this target Hertz we will
update what we're trying what the frame
rate is that we're trying to hit uh
dynamically so if the user has a
computer that can't even hit 30 frames
per second for some reason uh we will we
could drop down to 15 for example and
then the game will still run at the
right speed but the frame rate will be
very slow we could do that that now I
would argue that we should probably just
put up a big old box that says you got
to buy a new computer because you
shouldn't ever run a game at 15 frames a
second it's basically unplayable but we
can decide what we want to do at that
point much later down the line but we're
not we're not saying the game has a
fixed frame rate we're saying that we're
fixing the frame rate at any given time
so that we know when we're going to flip
so that our animation is consistent but
we can always change what that fixed
frame rate is if we want to and then the
game will always use whatever we tell it
is the frame rate to do its World
updating so we have the flexibility to
run it 60 30 uh 120 whatever we want to
run at based on the speed of the end
user's machine uh and the game will
respond
accordingly even if you could grab the
refresh rate of the monitor how do you
synchronize with it well uh so for our
prototype uh prototyping engine we won't
probably bother synchronizing with it
direct uh three uh direct draw
actually does have a thing that allows
you to wait for the vertical blank and
we could use that if we wanted to again
it depends if you want to use direct
draw which nowadays it's very deprecated
unfortunately I don't know why it would
be nice if they had maintained it um but
basically uh for our prototyping layer
we probably won't sync with the monitor
so that's fine because all that means is
that we'll be like off one frame
potentially or we'll get or we'll get
some tearing like a line down the middle
as as the as the the frame is flipped
but when we actually go to do the final
platform layer we'll be outputting
through open gel or direct 3D and those
have ability to set a flag that just
says automatically sync like when you do
a flip flip it with the monitor so we
won't have to worry about that that will
just be taken care of by the operating
system where we push a frame down it'll
automatically sync to it so we don't
actually have to do that ourselves for
the for the shipping
game doesn't the sleep function go in
the surrounding If instead of the while
loop um well it can go either place uh I
should think right um because basically
this should I mean one of the things we
should do obviously we we we could
certainly put it uh um well yeah we
could we could certainly put it here and
you would assume that that was that was
accurate uh but really the thing that I
I didn't do and need to do here uh is
make sure that we don't bother ever
calling the operating system is sleep
isn't zero so that's a bit of a mistake
and so yeah what the person was asking
is why don't we just do this outside and
they're totally right we can do it
outside because there's no need to do it
inside the while loop because the second
time through the while loop sleep
milliseconds is always going to be zero
presumably assuming we actually slept uh
for the time that we thought we were
going to sleep so I don't know yeah you
could put it out there you can put it in
here it doesn't actually matter where
you put it um as long as you check the
milliseconds to make sure that they're
greater than zero so I don't know
um I feel like if it's inside the while
loop it catches some problems like let's
say sleep doesn't sleep us for the time
for some reason because the operating
system just thought it was going to just
wake us up right right away again for
some reason then we just spin lock for
no reason and maybe we want to give the
operating system the chance to sleep us
again so I feel a little more
comfortable having it in here uh
although that said it does do one extra
computation which maybe we would argue
is bad for the spin lock so I don't know
um it's really hard to say I guess we'll
leave it out for now
um but I could go either way on that uh
and and whatever you want to do in your
version of this code uh you you can make
that judgment
call let's
see does win32 Phil sound buffer need to
come after the vsync loop uh yeah well
so we need to and I'll put in to-do just
so you guys know who are following along
at home who might be confused about that
uh where is okay so basically
um sound is wrong now because we haven't
updated it to go with the new frame Loop
uh so I haven't touched sound at all so
sound is just wrong um and I don't want
a patch sound right now like I don't
want to to fix this or anything um
because that's interesting I don't know
why this is a note should be oh I guess
it's just just saying it's the appest
let's get rid of that uh basically I
don't want to touch sound at all because
we're going to redo how we're doing the
sound timing so I want to do that in
line with with with the rest of it so
don't think about sound at all we
haven't looked at sound at all it's
totally wrong uh and doesn't obey the
diagram that I was drawing at the
beginning that I said that we wanted to
do so tomorrow our job is to make sound
line up with that
diagram
um check DW get composition timing info
on msdn if arrow is on well I'd rather
do something that that worked without
Arrow because I'd like to work on
Windows XP and the direct draw one does
work on uh on Windows XP so I probably
won't use that but thank you for
pointing that
out could you explain the potential
advantages or detriments to handling
update and render on separate timers
threads is there ever a good reason for
a programmer to update the game State
more frequently than they render it to
the
screen so no there isn't a good reason
to update the game State more often than
they render it to the to the
screen however there is a good reason
tightly related to that there is a good
reason why you may need to
subdivide some aspects of the update
into more granular updates than the
rendering and so the example of that
would
be let's say that your physics time step
needs to be one one 12th of a second but
your game frame rate is only 30 frames a
second well then you kind of are in a
situation where you're going to have to
run the physics update more frequently
uh so you have to kind of run it on a
subdivided time step um so there are
definitely ways that you could do that
with separate threads if you wanted to
there's there's a lot of different ways
you can approach that problem but
obviously the simplest one that doesn't
involve threading or any sort of stuff
like that is just to run the physics in
like a fouri loop inside the game update
it's basically like we're going to do
the update for the game we need to
update the physics four times for every
one update of the game so we just call
it four times with a with a quarter of
the time step and we're done uh so that
definitely does happen whether or not
you should multi-thread that and then
update the game at a different time I
mean I don't like that kind of thing but
I wouldn't necessarily say that it's
wrong because you can sort of see
Arguments for when why you might want to
do that I mean I don't know I don't love
it but but I I would be hesitant to say
that it was the wrong way to do things
it's just I I don't particularly love
that so I think it adds a lot of
complexity and I'm not sure you get a
lot of benefit for
it uh let's
see if we are locking no okay I already
answered
that um
how would you adjust your memory
management strategy for devices with
limited
memory uh we haven't done a memory
management strategy yet so wait until we
actually do our memory management and
then that should become clear I
think won't we miss frame rate due to
the sleep because while you're
truncating to millisecond you aren't
accounting for the up to 1 millisecond
granularity would just removing 1
millisecond from the weight
work um well I don't
think so because I mean basically this
is going to give us how many
milliseconds to sleep and it's going to
be fractional so this value is going to
come back like 10.3 milliseconds let's
say if we then truncate it we get 10
milliseconds that gives us3 milliseconds
uh of time that has to be spent spin
locking so I don't think we would miss
the frame rate at all there now there is
a separate problem which is that we're
not accounting for the fact that if we
actually were talking about doing doing
this in sync with something we would
want to account for how long this took
uh and wait for how much minus that but
we're in we're encapsulating all of the
time because we're using our end counter
uh we're we're we're always count
accounting for all the loop time because
we're subtracting from last counter
which gets s here so we're actually
accounting for the time that it takes to
flip as well uh but I don't know so I
don't actually think we would need to do
that but if the millisecond if the Sleep
milliseconds actually
um causes us to sometimes sleep an extra
millisecond then yes we would want to
subtract that now something we could do
here uh just for our own benefit is
assuming that we went uh through here
and did the target seconds per frame
thing and whatever we could uh assert
basically um that the first time when we
actually check the time here we could
assert uh that it that it is um like
like this right we could assert that
test seconds lapse for frame is greater
than zero right um or sorry is uh is is
less than Target seconds right to assert
that we didn't sleep too long we could
do that uh and we can see what happens
there um just to to see if we ever Miss
and we don't uh which which is what I
would expect right um so basically you
can see what I'm doing there is I'm just
saying hey look after we do the Sleep
let's verify that we didn't we didn't
like sleep past the frame time so we we
didn't do the thing that you were
worried about doing and so I don't think
it's it's going to do that um from the
readout here you do notice that this is
just not right like this should be
really close to
33.33 and it's not so we still have bugs
so I don't want to say that we're not
buggy um but I just I just don't think
that thing you're talking about is
actually happening or if it is happening
it's happening a different way uh
because it we should be we're asserting
this here and we now can see that um
that that's that's not actually the case
right um hopefully that's clear what's
happening there
garando Bloom says shouldn't tear if we
were in Window mode in Windows at least
unless people disable wdm Arrow yeah I
think I assume that Arrow does all of
its compositing on a flip so we
shouldn't see tearing but if you were on
Windows XP you might I don't know I I
I'm not sure depends on the operating
system and what you have
can you fix the physics animation frame
rate without fixing the graphics frame
rate so if you miss a frame just run the
physics more than once before rendering
the next frame no that that doesn't help
you you still showed the wrong thing
right uh we don't have to run the
physics multiple times because our
physics is going to allow large time
steps probably so we'll always have the
physics be able to run the right amount
of time uh to catch up to where it
thinks it should be uh but just to sort
of illustrate the the problem
here uh based on what you were sort of
saying so I'm going to go ahead and
clear this out um fantastic of course
that's exactly what I want to do is make
it tiny for some reason I do not
understand why it did that but that's
fine uh let's go ahead and zoom back in
there wait oh now the zoom is too what
what this does not look like a good
program
no smooth
draw
no no no no okay okay anyway uh so
basically what what I was uh trying to
say to that question is let's say we're
here and we've computed you know so
we're we're on our fixed frame rate so
we uh Advanced the world 16 milliseconds
right we Advanced the world we plus 16
milliseconds and we uh that was supposed
to show up here but we missed it because
we took too long and we ended up here so
it was basically a plus 16 millisecond
update uh and we end up with a 30
millisecond in interval right what I'm
trying to illustrate here is this is
wrong no matter what now it's just you
showed a wrong frame this Frame should
have been at plus 33 milliseconds in
physics time but it was actually at plus
16 milliseconds in physics time so it's
just wrong wrong wrong wrong it's all
wrong it is all wrong so what a lot of
people do is exactly what you're saying
and it's totally wrong what they do is
they then go okay I missed that so what
I'll do is uh it took 33 milliseconds so
I'll make this Frame add 33 milliseconds
to the time but now this Frame might
flip in 16 so now what you've done is
you've like wronged yourself twice this
is 2x wrong right so this is always
wrong and no don't like no much like
Smooth draw is no don't do it that way
what you need to do is try to figure out
how much time you think this Frame will
take to draw and that is how much you
need to update your physics by never use
the last frames time unless you then
decide that that is exactly how long
you're going to gate this Frame Time by
and you think you can hit it like the
previous frames time doesn't tell you
anything about this frame's time because
you don't know what happened on this
Frame it could have been that something
unusual happened on this Frame that
isn't going to happen on this Frame and
so they're not going to be similar times
so you need to be aware of all this
stuff and make good decisions instead of
just uh mindlessly forwarding um um that
last frame time to this Frame time
because that's just totally wrong a lot
of games do it and it's totally wrong
it's it's never
correct why are we handling sound and
video differently
um I'm afraid I'm not sure what that
means if you could tell me what you mean
by that I I will try to answer that
question I suspect it's probably a good
question but I'm just not sure exactly
what it means
uh let's
see brain criser check if Dr draw works
on Windows 8 I have problems with old
games that use it well yeah I mean we're
not actually going to use dra draw just
to be clear we would literally just use
the dra draw call that gets the monitor
refresh rate and then we'd test to see
if that was reliable we're not actually
going to use direct draw to draw um yeah
because I don't think that's very
supported it should be I wish they had
done
it wouldn't you want to fill the screen
buffer before you hit the frame flip
point so that the monitor could grab the
correct data when it refreshes well yes
but you have to remember we don't know
when the monitor is refreshing so all
we're doing here is we're just creating
a loop that will keep our game running
at 30 frames a second so that all of our
timing decisions will be correct later
when we do a win32 layer that outputs
through one of the modern graphic apis
like open jell direct 3D then that we
will have a different strategy of doing
exactly you're saying which is pushing
the frame down and then waiting and
letting the flip happen at the right
time but we don't even know when the
flip is happening here so we can't
actually do anything about that um
there's just no way so what we'd rather
do is wait the right amount of time here
before we flip so that we know that our
flips are always happening because
remember this is variable time up here
the game may take variable time to
update uh and this will take a constant
amount of time roughly or should so what
we want to do is wait to make sure we're
up at the 33 millisecond time then do
the flip right
there isn't dword an
integer
uh yes but
why sorry it's it's an unsigned 32-bit
integer but I don't understand the
question it is it is uh but if you could
if you could tell me why you were asking
that I may be able to uh clarify more if
that makes
sense sorry to go off topic but will the
art and Music Creation be live streamed
uh
no those are done by other people so so
that's a separate
thing what do you think about having a
fixed physics time unconnected to the
drawn frame Time by interpolating
positions of objects based on their time
differences um
the answer is I don't really know what I
think about it CU I've never done it
that
way there are some attractive features
of it which is that it it kind of lets
you have a more consistent gameplay
experience potentially if it's done
right because it would allow you to make
sure that the physics plays the same in
some sense on all platforms whether it's
a 50 HZ 60 HZ display something like
that
but I feel like you're doing a lot of
extra weird stuff there that may
actually end up giving you a worse
experience because the user is putting
input in at a time that actually is
before the time that is the latest thing
the physics already knows to be true so
the user actually now has input lag that
they wouldn't have had before and input
lag is not good for gameplay
experience so I really don't know I'd be
torn I I don't think it's a great idea
but maybe if you did it right it is so I
I don't know I can't speak to it really
in any other than a gut reaction because
I've never implemented a game that way
myself anytime you compute World update
shouldn't that just set something that
says if we get there early wait until
it's ready doesn't that also handle the
new Dynamic vsync stuff IE always wait
if you beat your time but if you miss
you get to update right when you're done
without
tearing uh yeah I mean that
is that is in some sense a quote unquote
benefit of the variable sync stuff but
the point is
never miss like you should never ever
ever miss your frame rate or it's going
to be a bad experience like unless you
only missed your frame rate by like a
tiny tiny
fraction in which case uh that maybe the
user couldn't perceive and maybe that's
a good thing about those variable vyncs
is like hey I missed it by just a tiny
tiny amount and flip then that's fine uh
but you kind of need to make sure you
never miss uh by anything other than the
tiniest fraction even in that case and
so if you can only ever Miss by the
tiniest fraction you should just just
not miss it all like I mean it's not
that different saying I have to hit 17
milliseconds versus 16.6 6666
milliseconds so I don't really see there
being that much of a difference between
those two things but you know um it is
what it is certainly it's not like bad
that they're doing the the variable sync
thing it's it's always better to have a
variable sync monitor because there's
more you could do with it right uh it's
it can only ever help it not going to
hurt unless they broke something when
they started doing that right so it is
always better to have a variable sync
monitor it's just
like I just don't know if it's worth the
cost or whatever that I mean it
eventually should presumably just be
free to kind of have that logic in there
or something and then we just always
want it but it's like do I really see
much of a benefit to it no it's like a
super super minor incremental thing like
it's not it's not a big deal I feel like
so that's that's all I was trying to say
about that I'm not trying to like pessim
those monitors entir like oh they're
crap I think they are better than what
we have they're just not much
better let's see I think that might be
all that might be
it that might be it are we done with the
Q&A are we is that it for Q&A I think we
may be done with the Q&A 5 minutes
early that is good stuff that is very
good
stuff all right well I mean I will wait
for another minute to see if there's any
last questions that come in to use up
our our our remaining now four minutes
but if not I think we have we have ended
the stream a little bit early even
though we started late we made good time
today although I really wished I could
have finished up sound today as well but
you know what we'll do it tomorrow so
that'll be fine so that will be fine
all right looks like there's no
questions coming in there uh looks looks
good all right well uh oh no oh well
there was a there was a bunch of s that
just came in there the minute earlier I
watched one of Chandler Caris talks
where he describes relationship between
data structures and algorithms in the
context of C++ performance he mentioned
that you could lose compiler
observations for an object by bringing
its address into it its identity could
you set some light on exactly what this
means I'd have to go rewatch it I'm not
sure what you mean by the phrase
bringing its address into its identity
but uh I I could go watch that and we
could talk about it on a future
stream uh so that's
good
um is it worth talking about timing
resolution in kernel or Too Deep uh well
I mean I think we can't really talk
about the timing resolution in the
kernel largely because we don't know
like the windows kernel is closed source
as far as I know I've never never seen
it so anything that I said that was
talking about the windows kernel would
kind of just be talking um you know
hypothetically in going off of like what
people post in msdn blog posts or
something uh so maybe there's a good
lecture out there uh there might be a
good lecture out there by a Windows
kernel guy who talks about the timing
and we could go by that uh but honestly
like I don't really know much about the
windows kernel timing I I don't know
what they do in there I know that time
begin period changes the kernel timing
uh but I don't actually know uh much
more much more than
that pretty sure Chandler was suggesting
passing by value because the compiler
had a lot of problems optimizing through
poers yes that is true but uh that
really only helps with
inlining I think he was talking about
inlining uh the optimizer you could
actually make your code slower by
passing things by value if it can't
inline them um because it would have to
actually do the copy uh so basically you
have to kind of know you kind of got to
actually look at what the compiler is
doing uh you can't just go always pass
by value always pass by pointer or
whatever you kind of have to say let me
see this code why is it slow and let me
see if I can make it faster by changing
the way certain things are passed to it
that so as a good rule of thumb super
small things always should be pass by
value obviously because it's easy to do
so uh and it's like if they're smaller
than eight bytes then they're smaller
than a pointer anyway so you should
always be passing Eight by things uh by
value you would think because passing
the pointer to them takes as much space
as passing them so you're only incurring
a speed hit but things that are
significantly bigger than a pointer 64
bite things let's say um 32 by things at
that point you may be getting into the
territory where you have to actually
know that the compiler really can
optimize it uh before you actually get a
win so so be careful I would say about
that that is what I would say all right
I think we are done with questions for
the day thank you so much for joining me
um and uh and I hope you also enjoyed
John stream earlier today I know I did
um if you would like uh for excuse me to
follow along at home with the source
code uh and the graphics assets once we
start working with Graphics which will
probably be next week I think uh you can
pre-order the game on handmad her.org
and you will get a link that allows you
to download the source code every night
you can go there as often as you want
and download the latest source code um
that is really easy to do and it has a
source code for all the days so you can
go jump back to any day and follow it
that way uh if you'd like to talk about
handmade hero there is this news and
forums link here which is pretty cool uh
you can go to the episode guide uh which
has a bunch of like annotated references
for past episodes you can go to the code
discussion page uh which has a bunch of
stuff uh that people um are talking
about and I answer questions on there as
well so if you have questions that's a
great place to post them uh all sorts of
stuff like that there's also uh if you
click on the handmade hero Central thing
the schedule for the week is always up
there so that you know what the hour is
going to be just a bunch of good stuff
so that's also a good place uh if you
want more handmade hero information so
thank you everyone for joining us uh I
will be back here again at 8:00 pm
Pacific Standard time tomorrow uh when
hopefully we will finish up our Loop and
then we can do a little fun stuff on
Friday have a little fun thing planned
we can do on Friday um which I don't
know how many people can make it to the
11:00 a.m. stream I know it's an odd
stream but we got a little fun thing we
can do
on Friday if we get through our
um if we can get through uh the the
sound stuff tomorrow so hopefully we
will thank you everyone for joining us I
will uh go update the source code and
the videos and I will see you here
tomorrow